It's all about asking the right questions. But it can unleash numerous opportunities for testing biological hypotheses. If our predictions match our observations, great! -- we got it right, so we can make further predictions by changing this or that aspect of the model. If, however, our predictions do not match our observations, that means that some of our assumptions are wrong, and so our understanding of the key mechanisms of underlying biology is still incomplete. Luckily, since this is a model, we control all the assumptions. So we can go through them, one by one, identifying which one or ones are causing the discrepancy. And then we can fill this newly identified gap in knowledge using both experimental and theoretical approaches. Of course, any ecosystem is extremely complex, and trying to describe all the moving parts is not only very difficult, but also not very informative. There's also the issue of timescales, because some processes take place on a scale of seconds, some minutes, some days, months and years. It may not always be possible to separate those out experimentally. And some things happen so quickly or so slowly that you may physically never be able to measure them. But as mathematicians, we have the power to zoom in on any subsystem in any timescale and simulate effects of interventions that take place in any timescale. Of course, this isn't the work of a modeler alone. It has to happen in close collaboration with biologists. And it does demand some capacity of translation on both sides. But starting with a theoretical formulation of a problem can unleash numerous opportunities for testing hypotheses and simulating scenarios and therapeutic interventions, all in a completely safe way. It can identify gaps in knowledge and logical inconsistencies and can help guide us as to where we should keep looking and where there may be a dead end. In other words: mathematical modeling can help us answer questions that directly affect people's health -- that affect each person's health, actually -- because mathematical modeling will be key to propelling personalized medicine. And it all comes down to asking the right question and translating it to the right equation ... and back. Thank you. (Applause)
Se trata de hacer las preguntas correctas. Pero puede crear numerosas oportunidades para evaluar hipótesis biológicas. Si nuestras predicciones coinciden con nuestras observaciones, ¡excelente!, acertamos y ya podemos hacer otras predicciones, cambiando tal o cual aspecto del modelo. Pero si nuestras predicciones no coinciden con nuestras observaciones, significa que son incorrectas algunas de nuestras suposiciones y que nuestro entendimiento de los mecanismos clave de la biología básica es aún incompleto. Por suerte, como este es un modelo, controlamos todos los supuestos. Y podemos analizarlos uno a uno e identificar cuál o cuáles ocasionan la discrepancia. Y luego podemos llenar este nuevo vacío de conocimiento mediante el uso de métodos experimentales y teóricos. Claro está que cualquier ecosistema es sumamente complejo, e intentar describir todas las piezas en movimiento no solo es difícil sino también muy poco informativo. También está el tema de las escalas temporales, porque algunos procesos ocurren en una escala de segundos, o minutos, o días, meses o años. Puede que no siempre sea posible separarlas experimentalmente. Y algunas cosas pasan a un ritmo tan lento o tan veloz que quizá nunca se las llegue a medir físicamente. Pero como matemáticos, tenemos el poder de focalizarnos en cualquier subsistema, en cualquier escala temporal, y simular los efectos de las intervenciones que ocurren en cualquier escala temporal. Es obvio que esta tarea no es solo del modelador. Debe haber una estrecha colaboración con los biólogos. Y sin dudas requiere de cierta capacidad para traducir de ambas partes. Pero comenzar con una formulación teórica de un problema puede crear numerosas oportunidades para evaluar hipótesis y simular escenarios e intervenciones terapéuticas de una manera absolutamente segura. Puede identificar vacíos de conocimiento y contradicciones lógicas y nos puede guiar por el camino correcto e indicarnos los posibles callejones sin salida. En otras palabras, los modelos matemáticos pueden ayudar a responder preguntas que afectan de forma directa a la salud de la gente; en realidad, la salud de cada uno de nosotros... porque la modelación matemática será clave para impulsar la medicina personalizada. Todo se reduce a hacer la pregunta correcta y traducirla a la ecuación correcta, y viceversa. Gracias. (Aplausos)